<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spirit of error, found and discovered, in the accounted pastors and teachers of the island Bermuda, in the VVest-Indies their principles and practice also tryed by the true spirit, and found to be contrary to the Scriptures of truth, and disproved by them, though pleaded for by the strongest arguments, the said teachers could bring forth : in an answer to some queries that were sent unto them, by us called Quakers : which answer was subscribed with all their names hereafter mentioned : their deceit unfolded for the peoples sake of the island / by ... Richard Pinder.</title>
            <author>Pinder, Richard, d. 1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54908</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10836</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13114294</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13114294</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97735</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54908)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97735)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 749:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spirit of error, found and discovered, in the accounted pastors and teachers of the island Bermuda, in the VVest-Indies their principles and practice also tryed by the true spirit, and found to be contrary to the Scriptures of truth, and disproved by them, though pleaded for by the strongest arguments, the said teachers could bring forth : in an answer to some queries that were sent unto them, by us called Quakers : which answer was subscribed with all their names hereafter mentioned : their deceit unfolded for the peoples sake of the island / by ... Richard Pinder.</title>
                  <author>Pinder, Richard, d. 1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Bermuda Islands.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97735:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97735:1"/>
            <head>The SPIRIT of ERROR, Found, and Diſcovered, In the accounted <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> of the Iſland <hi>Bermuda,</hi> in the <hi>VVeſt-Indies;</hi> Their Principles and Practice alſo tryed by the True <hi>Spirit,</hi> and found to be contrary to the Scriptures of Truth, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by them; though pleaded for by the ſtrongeſt Arguments, the ſaid <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> could bring forth. In an Anſwer to ſome <hi>Queries</hi> that were ſent unto them, by us called <hi>Quakers.</hi> Which Anſwer was ſubſcribed with all their Names hereafter mentioned. Their deceit unfolded for the Peoples ſake of the <hi>Iſland;</hi> By a Servant of the Truth, (which ſearches out all iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, though it work in a Myſtery) called, RICHARD PINDER.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>The Wicked is ſnared by the tranſgreſſion of his Lips, but the Juſt ſhall come out of trouble.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 12.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Day of Glory hath appeared, &amp; the everlaſting Goſpel is now Preached unto them that dwel upon the earth, to the calling all forth off that great and long night of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which hath lain over <hi>every Nation, Kinred, Tongue,</hi> and <hi>People;</hi> where the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophet <hi>hath Reigned,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Myſterie Babylon, the Mother of Harlots <hi>deceived;</hi>
               </hi> that they upon whom ſhe hath ſitten, have been <hi>as unſtable as the Waters,</hi> and <hi>as changeable as the Windes,</hi> that a Rock, or Place to reſt upon they have not known; but toſſed and hurried to to and fro they have been, and deceived on every hand, through her Inchantments, that have filled the whole Earth with ſpoil and violence, through her changeable Waies and Garments, which ſhe hath been decked
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97735:2"/>withall, ſince ſhe began to drink the Saints Blood, and ſince ſhe, <hi>Myſterie Babylon,</hi> the <hi>falſe Church,</hi> made all. Nations drunk with the Wine of her Fornications, which hath made them Reel and Stagger to and fro, that they have all loſt the way, and turned into the by-paths, wherein they are groaping like blind men without any glimmering of Light, and run and claſh one againſt another, and fall on heaps, and then burſt out like the Waters, thinking to ſwallow all up; and then another Wave meets them, and here ariſes Heat and Rage one againſt another; and here People rend and tear one another about the Scriptures, and cry it up to be their Rule and Guide to lead them to knowledge; but have all loſt the Key which ſhould open the Door of true Knowledge, and which ſhould open the Scriptures unto them; and this Key they hate <hi>(which is the Light which Chriſt hath enlightened every one withall;)</hi> and ſo it is but juſt on the Lords behalf, to give every one of them up to follow the Imaginations of their own hearts, being that they hate his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, and caſt his Law behind their backs: And being that they are grown ſo proud and haughty, that they deſpiſe waiting for his Counſel, that every one doth the thing which ſeemeth good in his own eyes; and there the Lord and his Reproofs are not regarded, but rejected; neither is his Law there waited for: Where man hath choſen his own way, in which man ſeeks to exalt himſelf, and to get a name in the Earth, that what man doth in that ſtate, he hath a ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end in it; whether it be in matters ſeemingly to bring ſomething to the glory of God, or in others; yet he hath his own end in it, and this is the eſtate where man is Curſed, and all things (unto him) for his ſake; and there man is ſeparated from the true and living God, and ſo turned into his own Inventions; invents a way to ſerve and worſhip him, by whom he was made, thinking thereby to pleaſe him, and procure his love: Whenas, alas, he daily rejects his love, by turning into his own waies; and here the Lords hand is turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt man, becauſe of his iniquity, which daily aboundeth, and is daily brought forth, where man hath choſen his own way, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the way of God, <hi>which is but one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the waies which man hath invented, are <hi>many;</hi> and which he hath ſought out for himſelf, ſince he was turned forth of the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God; by reaſon of his chuſing to walk in his own waies, And there ſtandeth the craft and ſubtilty of man, in the degenerate ſtate, degenerated through the ſubtilty and craft of him, that hath
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97735:2"/>led from the Truth, that he cannot ſavour the things of God, his Judgement and Diſcerning being taken away; and in that he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come leavened up into ſuch a temper and frame, as he is altogether an Enemy to Truth and Righteouſneſs. In this ſtate, <hi>man calls <hi>Truth Error,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Error Truth;</hi> and calls, and accounts <hi>his own way,</hi> the <hi>way of Righteouſneſs;</hi> and ſo puts <hi>the Lords VVay,</hi> and <hi>his Judgements</hi> afar off; and ſeeketh to do thoſe things which is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in his own eyes; and by this perverteth true Judgement, and ſeeketh to be Judge himſelf over the things which God hath made; and there man is not at all willing that God ſhould rule over the work of his own hands, but would rule, and be Lord and King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and ſo goeth on in craft and ſubtilty, as that Power worketh and moveth in him, which is at enmity againſt God; for its King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Exaltation ſtandeth in craft and ſubtilty, and there its ſtrength lyeth by which it is upholden; oppoſing the Lord and his Work, and ſetting its own up, in thoſe who are guided by it, and ſo it hath many Inſtruments which in ſubtilty and craft, under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Godlineſs will ſtand up for it, in oppoſition to the way by which God worketh to manifeſt his love among the ſons of men, to reconcile them unto himſelf again; which is onely known through his own Son, which in his love he gave a Light into the world, <hi>that whoſoever ſhould believe in him, ſhould not abide in Darkneſs</hi> (by which people are ſeparated from God) <hi>but ſhould have the Light of Life.</hi> And this is He, by which God maketh himſelf known unto the ſons of men, that through tranſgreſſion have been deſtitute of his knowledge; and this Word of Reconciliation being now Preached, even the Goſpel of his onely begotten Son, in whom the Father is well pleaſed, and in which man is accepted with him again; I ſay, This Goſpel being now Preached unto <hi>every Nation, Kinred, Tongue,</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> over whom <hi>the Beaſt,</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophet <hi>have reigned,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Myſterie Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Mother of Harlots <hi>bewitched.</hi>
               </hi> Alſo now the Power of the enmity ſtandeth up on every Inſtrument <hi>(whom it hath fitted)</hi> to blaſpheme &amp; reproach the Goſpel of Light, and glad Tidings; which we the deſpiſed people <hi>(commonly called Quakers)</hi> bear teſtimony unto, though for it we are <hi>Hated,</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed,</hi> and <hi>ſpoken againſt,</hi> in every place, by them that have pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be Preachers of the Goſpel of Peace and glad Tidings; but are now in this the day of Glory, found to be Preachers for the glory of man, and for filthy Lucre, &amp; are now found to be <hi>of Myſterie Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylons
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97735:3"/>Merchants,</hi> which have long deceived the Nations, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their money for that which is not Bread; which now, when the day of Glory hath appeared, and their Merchandize ſpoiled, begin <hi>to lament</hi> and <hi>mourn;</hi> and becauſe in a day <hi>miſery is come upon them,</hi> in which they gnaw their Tongues for pain, and blaſpheme againſt the Lord and his Tabernacle, which now is witneſſed to be with men; whoſe day hath appeared, to make their abominations mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and to the diſcovering of the ſecrets of their hearts, that their Blaſphemy againſt the Lord and his Tabernacle, they utter forth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their ſorrow that is come upon them: For <hi>though they cry to the <hi>Mountains</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Hils</hi> to <hi>cover them,</hi> yet <hi>they cannot defend them; for a conſumption is determined againſt them, &amp; entred into their own bowels; that Behold, when they look for <hi>Day, Night</hi> then cometh upon them;</hi> and <hi>when they look for <hi>ſafety</hi> from the <hi>Hils</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, <hi>even ſudden deſtruction cometh upon them, that Blackneſs of Darkneſs compaſſeth them about;</hi>
               </hi> and the deeper they dive to hide their counſel from the Lord, the greater will their miſery be, and the ſooner will their meaſure of iniquity be filled up, that the Lord with the Beeſom of his wrath may ſweep them away. For do we read in all the Scriptures, that the <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> in any generation uttered forth <hi>ſuch folly</hi> and <hi>Ignorance,</hi> as the <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> in this generation do? And though you three of <hi>Bermuda</hi> lay long hid, that the envy which was in your hearts againſt the heritage of God, did not ſo much appear, as it did in ſome of your Brethren; yet the Lord hath ſought you out, that the deceit of your hearts might be made manifeſt, and laid open; and that was the end for which I was moved <hi>to ſend my Queries unto you;</hi> and not that I wanted ſatisfaction as to my own particular, in the things <hi>whereof I Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried;</hi> but that your Belief and Judgement might be brought forth: For, as many may know, you are the leaſt of many hundreds of the men of Darkneſs, which have uttered forth their folly and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, in paſſing their judgements <hi>upon us,</hi> (whom God hath made <hi>as a terrour unto all the wicked</hi>) and upon the Goſpel of Light, which we bear teſtimony unto, <hi>which hath enlightned every one that cometh into the World;</hi> about which <hi>Light,</hi> the moſt of my Queries unto you was, which were ſent unto you, ſubſcribed with <hi>my own name,</hi> and with <hi>George Rofé,</hi> who alſo hath given his teſtimony againſt you, both by his Word and Writing. And I having now received an Anſwer to my Queries, I may here ſet down ſome of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97735:3"/>your principal Arguments laid down therein, with my Reply unto them, that both may be ſent into the World, that all who fear the Lord may judge thereof.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay, in anſwer to the firſt Querie, <hi>That there may be a light in man, reproving and convincing of ſin, and yet not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to lead unto life.</hi> For they ſay: <hi>Such a light was in Judas.</hi> And they ſay, <hi>There is a Natural Light in man, which Reproveth ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The Light which convinceth the World of ſin, is the Spirit of Truth; and Chriſt ſaid, <hi>It ſhould lead them into all Truth,</hi> Joh. 16.8. So, for you three Prieſts to ſay, <hi>that the Light which convinceth of ſin, is not ſufficient to lead unto Life;</hi> you might as well ſay, <hi>Christ ſpoke not truth,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>That the Spirit which reproveth the World of ſin, ſhould lead into all Truth.</hi> And <hi>Judas</hi> he turned from the Truth, when he betrayed the Innocent into the hands of ſinners. And when he took money <hi>(of ſuch envious men as you are)</hi> for ſo doing, in whom a perſecuting ſpirit ſoon appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; as you may remember, your ſeeking to the Magiſtrates to have us baniſhed, who witneſſed againſt all deceit, and deeds of Darkneſſe, and againſt your natural Light, and againſt your Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by your Natural Learning, which the Light that convinceth of ſin, diſcovereth to be contrary to what the Apoſtles Preached; who received their Goſpel not of man, neither was taught it by man,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.1.</note> but by the Revelation of Chriſt; who hath enlightned every one that cometh into the World, that through him all might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and receive life; But his Light condemns all ſuch Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers as you are.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay in their Anſwer to another Querie, <hi>That the Light which diſcovereth corruption, is from Chriſt, but not given to all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The <hi>Light</hi> which diſcovereth corruption, <hi>is One in all;</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 3.</note> the ſame <hi>to him that believeth,</hi> as it is <hi>in him that believeth not.</hi> For Chriſt, whoſe Light convinceth of ſin, is He that is to judge all Nations of men, that be upon the face of the whole earth: Yea all you Unbelievers are to be judged by him; and according to the <hi>Light (which he hath enlightned you withal)</hi> will Judgement be given, and you receive reward according to your deeds.</p>
            <p>So it is good for you all now, while you have time, to give re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Light which convinceth of ſin, and diſcovereth the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97735:4"/>corruptions of your own hearts, and it will let you ſee, that ſuch as ſay all are not enlightned with a meaſure of it, are Deceivers, and ſpeak contrary to the Scriptures in ſo ſaying: As you may read 1 <hi>John, v.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay again, <hi>That light may be in a man two wayes.</hi> Firſt they ſay, <hi>By proceeding from In-bred Principles brought into the World with him, as water is in a Well, where it ſpringeth.</hi> Secondly, They ſay, <hi>Light may be in a man by infuſion, or inſtruction, by him that wanted it, as water is put into a Well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Where do you read, that any <hi>of the true Prophets, Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>his Apoſtles,</hi> told people <hi>of light being in them two waies?</hi> This is but a piece of Sophiſtry, to blind people withall, to tell them of light <hi>being in them two waies.</hi> And ſee how in this you are contrary to the Scriptures: For did not the Lord ſay, <hi>He would give a Light to the Gentiles, which ſhould be his ſalvation unto the ends of the earth? Iſa.</hi> 49. And doth not <hi>Simeon</hi> ſay of Chriſt, <hi>That he was given a Light, to lighten the Gentiles? Luke</hi> 2.32. And did not Chriſt himſelf ſay, <hi>I am the Light of the World? John</hi> 8.12. And did not he ſay, <hi>It was the Condemnation that Light was come into the World, and men loved <hi>Darkneſs</hi> rather</hi> than Light; <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their deeds were evil? John</hi> 3.19. And did not <hi>John</hi> ſay, <hi>He enlightneth every one that cometh into the World? John</hi> 1.9. And did not the Apoſtle ſay, <hi>That the light which ſhined in their hearts, gave them the Light of the Knowledge of the glory of God, in the face <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Jeſus?</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p>So you that are ſpeaking of two Lights, are them that darkens Counſel, by uttering words without knowledge, who tell <hi>of an In-bred light, which is as water ſpringing in a VVell;</hi> and <hi>of light infuſed, which is as water put into a VVell:</hi> That you three Prieſts may read your ſelves by your own compariſon, who tell people <hi>of light being infuſed into them,</hi> by hearing you tell your meanings of the Scriptures, and their meanings whom you call Orthodox men; (which <hi>you call Preaching of the VVord</hi>) that I ſay you may read your ſelves, and alſo your Hearers by your Compariſon, who <hi>compare that Light</hi> (which <hi>is infuſed into people by inſtruction, which you count your work</hi>) <hi>to water that is put into a VVell.</hi> Now conſider, Will not water that is put into a Well that hath no Spring in it ſoon decay, and waſte away? But Praiſes be unto the Lord, who among his (that <hi>have believed in the Light which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97735:4"/>enlightneth every one that cometh into the VVorld</hi>) hath opened the Well-ſpring of Light; and Life; and ſuch ſee your ignorance, and laugh at your folly, who are ſpeaking of Light being in people two waies; you are the men of Darkneſs, whoſe eyes the god of the World hath blinded; leſt you ſhould ſee the Light of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Goſpel, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay, That <hi>there is a light within ſome men, diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their corruptions; what it is,</hi> and <hi>where it is; by Infuſion,</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; by the VVord of God contained in the Scripture;</hi> That <hi>(they ſay) they grant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> What will the Light which cometh by Inſtruction, which you your ſelves <hi>compare to water put into a VVell;</hi> (which will ſoon waſte and decay) <hi>will it diſcover corruption, where it is,</hi> and <hi>what it is?</hi> And will not <hi>the Light which is in people,</hi> which <hi>is as water that ſpringeth in a VVell,</hi> will <hi>not this diſcover corruption,</hi> and <hi>where it is?</hi> By this you are ſeen to be they which would ſet up your ſelves. For we know well enough what it is you call the Word of God, contained in the Scriptures:<note place="margin">1 Kings 8.17.</note> But the Word of God is Chriſt, which the Heaven of Heavens cannot contain. So in this you have ſhewed forth your ignorance.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay in Anſwer to another Querie, which was, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Light (by which the Children of Light walked) was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, or ſome Light without them?</hi> To this they ſay, <hi>The light whereby the Children of Light walked, was within them; root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and grafted in their hearts: but it was infuſed into them by the Doctrine contained in the holy Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The LIGHT, which the Children of <hi>Light</hi> (which we read of in Scripture) <hi>walked in;</hi> and in which they had fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with God, and one with another; and in which they knew the blood of Jeſus, which cleanſed from all ſin: God was the Author <hi>of this Light,</hi> John 1.5. and not <hi>the Scripture:</hi> For the Scripture doth but declare <hi>of the Light:</hi> Neither doth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſay <hi>(as you do)</hi> in any place, <hi>that Light by them is infuſed into people:</hi> but ſaith, <hi>Chriſt, the Light, by which every one is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened.</hi> And ſeveral there were, which walked in the Light with God, before the Scriptures were written; as <hi>Enoch, who was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated from death to life,</hi> Gen. 5.22. and <hi>Abraham</hi> knew the voice of God before the Scriptures were written.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.5.</note> And why do you tell ſo often <hi>of Light being infuſed into people by the Doctrine contained in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97735:5"/>the Scriptures;</hi> and do not alſo tell what you mean by that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? Now if this be your meaning (as I believe it is) your ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Verſe of the Scriptures, and raiſe from it <hi>ſo many Doctrines,</hi> and then lay down ſo many <hi>Tryals,</hi> and then ſo many <hi>Arguments,</hi> and then ſo many <hi>Motives,</hi> and <hi>Uſes,</hi> and <hi>Applications:</hi> if this be the Doctrine you ſo much ſpeak-of (as I ſay again, I believe it is) through which you ſay <hi>Light muſt be infuſed into people.</hi> Now conſider, you do all this for money; and people give you money for doing of it, as you three Prieſts; <hi>witneſs your Forty pound Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary,</hi> and <hi>two ſhares of Land a year:</hi> yet nevertheleſs, though you do all this for money; the gift of God cannot be bought and ſold for money, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.20. And they that walked <hi>in the LIGHT</hi> (which is the gift of God) they witneſſed a cleanſing from the ſin through it; which you, who tell of <hi>Light being infuſed into people</hi> (by ſuch Doctrine as before mentioned) <hi>plead againſt;</hi> that in ſhort, we plainly ſee, the more people adhere unto you, the further into darkneſs they are led, and the further they are from owning the gift of God in themſelves; which ſhould lead them unto Life Eternal, and from the teaching of all Deceivers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.13.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay, <hi>The Children of Light came to a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Scriptures, through the Light that ſhined in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures themſelves; and not by any Light that was in them before they were acquainted with the Scriptures. As a man in the dark diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Candle, by the light which ſhineth from the Candle; and not by any light he had before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That which muſt bring people to receive a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Scriptures, is the Spirit which leads to the fulfilling of them: for many there were that had the Scriptures, and could talk of them, and yet were in darkneſſe, and could not ſee into the myſtery the Scripture ſpoke of, in that they were enemies to the Spirit by which they were ſpoken forth; and ſo ſtumbled at CHRIST,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.23. Rom. 9.32.</note> the <hi>True Light;</hi> Him of whom the Scriptures did declare: But <hi>Simeon,</hi> who was a Juſt man, and waited for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> it was revealed unto him by the holy Ghoſt; <hi>that he ſhould not ſee death, until he had ſeen the Lords Chriſt,</hi> Luk. 2.26. Now he did not ſay, <hi>that the Scriptures did reveal this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him,</hi> but <hi>the holy Ghoſt.</hi> For there were many at that time, who did expect the <hi>Meſſias</hi> to come; as <hi>Simeon</hi> did: yet though they had the Scriptures, yet could not know him, who was the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97735:5"/>Light,</hi> and <hi>Iſraels Glory,</hi> Luk. 2.32. And now you three Prieſts, conſider your compariſon; Whether a man by the light of a Candle only, diſcerneth the light of a Candle, as you ſay; or he diſcerneth the Candle, and its light, by his eye, which is the light of the body, which he had before: for a man that hath not the light of the eye, he can neither ſee the Candle, nor its light. That you have erred both in the main matter, and in your compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, and by your own compariſon, may be judged to be men,<note place="margin">Deut. 16.19.</note> whoſe eye, gifts and rewards hath blinded, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13, 8. (to wit) ſuch yearly gifts, as <hi>your forty pound Salary,</hi> and <hi>two ſhares of Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay in their Anſwer to another Query; <hi>That they do not promiſe to bring any light of their own to the Scriptures,</hi> as they ſay, our words in our Queries would make; but, they ſay, <hi>they on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do open the words, and ſeek out the true ſence contained in them, by an Allegory of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We know, whatever you profeſs or promiſe, that you can bring <hi>no light to the Scriptures;</hi> and for your finding out <hi>the true ſence of them,</hi> that alſo we know you can never do, ſo long as you are not guided by the ſame Spirit, as they were that ſpoke them forth, though you have them in ſeveral Languages, as <hi>Latine, Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew,</hi> as <hi>Pilate</hi> had, who delivered the Innocent up into the hands of blood-thirſty-men: ſuch <hi>Nathaniel White,</hi> as thy Brethren in <hi>New-England</hi> are: whom thou ſo highly extolls, and art a Paſtor of their falſe Church, which is of <hi>Myſtery Babylons off-ſpring;</hi> witneſs their drinking the Saints blood. And though thou, with thy two Brethren, <hi>Brown</hi> and <hi>Burre,</hi> tell of <hi>ſearching out the true ſence of the Scripture, by an Allegory of Faith;</hi> yet we know ſo long as you live in headineſs, high-minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and love Pleaſures more than God; and accuſe falſly, as you many times did us, (who witneſſed againſt your deceit) we know ſo long as you are ſuch, <hi>that your minds are corrupt,</hi> and that you are <hi>reprobate cancerning the Faith,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.8. <hi>which was orce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Saints,</hi> before <hi>Myſtery Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.4.</note> your Churches Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, brought forth ſuch Children as you are; who live in Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſporting your ſelves in the day-time, as <hi>Nathaniel White;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet 2.13.</note> witneſs thy playing <hi>at Bowls;</hi> and yet by <hi>New-Englands falſe Church,</hi> and Gathered Congregations, is accounted a <hi>Reverend Divine.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:97735:6"/>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay, That <hi>to ſay their Preaching is nothing elſe but the telling people of their own meanings of the Scriptures, is an untruth; and that we are never able to prove it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Are not you the very men that get your living by telling the people your meanings of the Scriptures? for do you not deny the Light which <hi>Chriſt hath enlightned every one withall;</hi> which ſhould reveal the Myſtery the Scripture ſpeaks of, which is, <hi>God manifeſt in the fleſh:</hi> Do you not deny this? and tell people, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation is not to be looked for in theſe dayes:</hi> And what do you ſay, <hi>it is an untruth to ſay you give your own meanings of the Scriptures?</hi> If an untruth; how comes it to paſſe then, that you three Prieſts are not all of one judgment? for certainly if you were guided by that Spirit, by which the Scriptures were given forth, it would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your Judgment, and bring you into <hi>oneneſs of mind;</hi> but you being enemies unto the Spirit, by which the Saints were led, you cannot agree in your meanings about the Scriptures, though you are made friends, and agree in this thing to joyn your ſtrength to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt the Truth, as <hi>Pilate,</hi> and <hi>Herod:</hi> But formerly have you not been at difference among your ſelves? and are you not ſo ſtill, even about that you call <hi>Church-Government;</hi> and about thoſe things you ſay are <hi>Inſtitutions of Chriſt;</hi> your <hi>ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Infants;</hi> and giving people <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> which you call a <hi>Sacrament?</hi> which indeed <hi>both</hi> it, and your <hi>sprinkling of Infants</hi> are from the POPE, and ware inſtituted by him: but as for your not agreeing among your ſelves about theſe things, I need ſay little; and alſo for your joyning together againſt the Truth: Theſe things I may both leave to them of that Iſland, who fear the Lord, to judge of: for they take notice of your unſtableneſs; and the day is now coming, wherein (it may be) you may be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tryed. But all will be, that the deceit and rottenneſs of your hearts may appear unto all, that deſire truly to fear the Lord, that they with ſpeed may turn from following you in your pernicious wayes, leſt they be deſtroyed with you; for the ſnare is before you.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay again, <hi>They uſe the help of Faithful and Orthodox mens Labours; whom God hath commanded them to remember,</hi> and <hi>to follow their faith; againſt which way</hi> (they ſay) <hi>we, nor any other can except any thing juſtly.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97735:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We can juſtly except againſt, and have already ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted <hi>againſt both you,</hi> and them you account <hi>Orthodox mens Labours;</hi> for are not you of the generation of men, who by their Opinions, and by them they count Orthodox mens O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, have ſet people on heaps, like one to deſtroy ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe they are not of the ſame Opinion with them: And hath not this been the work, ſince the Opinions of thoſe you call Orthodox men, were cryed up; and ſince you (the Merchants of <hi>Myſtery Babylon</hi>) told people, <hi>they muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Faith of thoſe you call Orthodox men;</hi> whoſe faith you ſay <hi>you are commanded to follow:</hi> But alas! do not they differ in their Opinions as much as you? that have not people, by adhering to their works, which you traded withall, been driven into <hi>divers Opinions, Sects</hi> and <hi>VVayes;</hi> and then ſeek to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy one another about them? and by this, are not you, and your Brethren found to be they, that have cauſed ſo much Blood to be ſhed among them, that have the name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? And why do you three Prieſts not tell us where you have a Command from God, to follow the Faith of them you call Orthodox men, ſeeing you ſay you have? But doth it not plainly appear by this, that you are the men who have erred from the Faith, <hi>which was once delivered to the Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 15.9.</note> and which the Saints lived in; which gave them victory over the world, and purified their hearts.<note place="margin">Eph 2.8.</note> For is not this the Faith which you have received by tradition from thoſe you account Orthodox men; That people cannot be free from ſin, while here upon earth? Now if this be the Faith of the Orthodox men, which you ſay you are to follow; then we can juſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>both againſt them</hi> and <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>your Faith,</hi> for it is not the Faith of Gods Elect: for they that were <hi>in it,</hi> witneſſed <hi>victory</hi> over the world <hi>through it,</hi> and were ſaved from ſin <hi>by it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh 5.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay, <hi>It is a lye to ſay they do not exhort people to come to the knowledge of the Scriptures, as the free gift of God;</hi> for they ſay in their Doctrine, <hi>they declare it as a gift of Grace given to ſome, and not all; we exhort them to beg it of God by Prayer; and before we preach, we pray with them, and for them, to God, that he would beſtow the right underſtanding of his Word, upon them, and us,</hi> they ſay.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97735:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That which gives a true underſtanding in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (which you call the Word) is the gift of God, which is <hi>his Grace, which hath appeared unto all men,</hi> Tit. 2.11. And you that deny, and would exclude <hi>this Grace,</hi> from having <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto all men;</hi> are ſetting up your own Doctrines and Commandments, received by Tradition, and are crying them up, and ſelling them to your hearers for money; and though you both preach, and pray with them before you preach; yet, have you not money for your Praying, as well as your Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? And though you exhort people <hi>to beg by prayer from God, a right underſtanding of his Word;</hi> yet, have you not money for this Exhortation? But Praiſes be unto the Lord, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong His hath manifeſted his Word of Life to inſtruct; which <hi>is nigh them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 30.14.</note>
               <hi>even in their mouths, and in their hearts, that they may hear it, and obey it.</hi> And ſuch who know the Inſtructions of the Word, which gives Life; they deny your <hi>Inſtructions,</hi> and <hi>Exhortations,</hi> and <hi>Preaching,</hi> and <hi>Praying</hi> alſo: for they ſee that you do them all but for your own ends, ſince you have ſet your ſelves againſt the Truth; as you three Prieſts of <hi>Bermuda</hi> have done; who were like a wild Bull in a Net: witneſs your <hi>fretting</hi> and <hi>chafing</hi> in your <hi>Praying</hi> and <hi>Preaching,</hi> when you could not get the Magiſtrates of that place to ſatisfie your envious minds, <hi>to baniſh us off that Iſland;</hi> who came to viſit the remnant of <hi>Jacobs Seed;</hi> that it might be gathered from off the tops of the barren Mountains (where it long had been ſcattered) into the Fold of Reſt; and at the fulfilling of this your rage (like mad-men) appeared.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay, That <hi>they find to their great comfort, that the Doctrine of holy Scriptures, received by Faith, hath power to purge their hearts from the Corruption of Sin;</hi> and they ſay, <hi>it's often declared by them, that they own no other Light of Chriſt, making to ſee ſin to their ſalvation, but this Doctrine contained in the holy Scripture, and planted into their hearts by his holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, through hearing and reading of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By this it appeareth, that you are them that preach up another Faith, than that which was preached <hi>to Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> before the Scriptures were written, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8. when <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> ſaw the coming of the Juſt Ones, and rejoyced, <hi>Ioh.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97735:7"/>8.58. And the Prophet ſaith, <hi>He ſhould ſit as a Refiner and Purifier of Silver,</hi> Mal. 3.3. And <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>He ſhall through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purge his floor,</hi> Luke 3.17. And the Scriptures cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him, for <hi>he is aſcended for above all heavens, that he might fill all things,</hi> Epheſ. 4.10. This is He the Scripture declares of, who was the <hi>Author and Finiſher of the Saints Faith;</hi> in whom they believed, and had remiſſion of ſins; and received Life Everlaſting, according as the Scriptures ſay: And <hi>the Spirit of Truth, which led them into all Truth, was the Saints Comforter,</hi> and this led them to the fulfilling of what before was written: And ſo they ſtumbled not at Chriſt the chief corner-ſtone, as they did that cryed up the <hi>Prophets VVritings,</hi> but were erred from the Spirit, <hi>by which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets were led:</hi> and this is your condition, who ſet your ſelves to ſcandalize and reproach <hi>the LIGHT, which Chriſt hath enlightned every one withal;</hi> and yet are crying up the Doctrine contained in the Scripture; and ſay, <hi>it hath power to purge your hearts from the corruption of ſin:</hi> when as alas, you believe no ſuch thing, as people can be purged wholly from ſin in this life. And note, that ſo long as ſin remaineth, it corrupts; and ſo your deceit is ſeen, who tell of <hi>being purged from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption;</hi> and not <hi>from the ſin which doth corrupt.</hi> And Praiſes be unto the Lord, many are come into the Faith, <hi>by which</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel <hi>offered a more acceptable ſacrifice than</hi> Cain;<note place="margin">Heb. 11.4, 25.</note> of whoſe ſtock all envious men are: And the <hi>Faith of</hi> Abraham <hi>is witneſſed,</hi> by which he obeyed the voice of God, before the Scriptures were written; and <hi>faith which Moſes was in, is witneſſed,</hi> by which he denyed the pleaſure of ſin, which you three Prieſts are yet found in; and though you cry up the Doctrine contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Scriptures, yet your deceit is ſeen, and your Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance diſcovered, who ſay, <hi>You know no Light of Chriſt making to ſee ſin to your ſalvation, but the Doctrine contained in the Scriptures;</hi> which before I ſhewed what it was, taking a Verſe of Scripture, and Divining an hour (by a Glaſs) from it: But all ſuch Doctrine, they that ſpoke forth the Scripture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, and preached Chriſt the Light, and Lamb of God, which had been ſlain from the foundation of the World, and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed remiſſion of ſins through him, who is the Power of God, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97735:8"/>the Righteouſneſs of God, who hath enlightned every one that cometh into the World, that through him all might believe. And <hi>this Light</hi> the Saints witneſſed <hi>to ſhine in their hearts, to give them the Light of the knowledge of the Glory of God.</hi> And ſo this Light they preached, which in all at firſt ſhined in Darkneſs, and reproves for the ſin that is brough forth by the Power of Darkneſs.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay, <hi>That we</hi> (to wit the <hi>Quakers</hi>) <hi>take the Light of Chriſt for the knowledge of Chriſt, as the Son of God, and Saviour of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> He that is the onely begotten Son of God, and Saviour of the World, <hi>hath enlightned every one that cometh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the VVorld;</hi> and this is he that giveth the knowledge of the Father; and <hi>this is life eternal, to know the Father, and him whom he hath ſent a Light into the VVorld,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 12.36.</note> that <hi>they who belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in him, ſhould not abide in Darkneſs.</hi> Now the Light which cometh from the onely begotten of the Father, Firſt ſheweth unto people their own darkneſs, to the end, that with the Light they may be led out of it; that where the Light is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in, and obeyed, it manifeſteth life; which life Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and Reconcileth unto God as it is known. And this is the true and ſaving knowledge of Chriſt, which we (the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi>) bear teſtimony unto; for by his Life the Saints were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and this Life none know,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.10.</note> but who come and wait in the Light for the revealing of it, that they are the Children which abide in the Darkneſs, who do not believe in the Light, which Chriſt hath enlightned every one that cometh into the World withall, and can never come to the knowledge which ſaveth, but are condemned already, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.18.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay, <hi>To reaſon from every one having ſo much light, as leaveth them without excuſe; therefore they have a Light of Chriſt, or ſaving Light</hi> (they ſay) <hi>its all alike; as if one ſhould prove every ſick man hath knowledge to recover himſelf, becauſe he knoweth he is ſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Here would you not make it, as though people were left without excuſe by ſome <hi>other light,</hi> than the Light <hi>of Chriſt.</hi> Oye blind Leaders of the blind, who are thus fallen into the Pit of darkneſs! Doth not Chriſt, who is the Light,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97735:8"/>and ſaveth them that believe in him, condemn the Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers? And would you have him to judge and condemn them for their ſin and tranſgreſſion, and that he never enlightned them, to let them ſee what ſin and tranſgreſſion was? Oh how you erre in the things of God, and in the judgement which is Eternal, which is committed unto the Son, who hath enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned every man that cometh into the World. And you that are telling <hi>of a Light, by which people are left without excuſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 9.22.</note> and <hi>not from Chriſt,</hi> you are they that are ſetting up another Judge than he; and ſo would pervert the Truth, and true judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which was ever the work of him that is the father of Lyes, who did not abide in the Truth, whoſe waies the true Light now diſcovereth; that though you who are filled with his ſubtilty, go about never ſo many waies to pervert the Truth and true Judgement; yet you are diſcovered in them all, and all your <hi>Arguments</hi> and <hi>Compariſons</hi> ſeen to be of <hi>no value.</hi> For conſider your laſt Compariſon: <hi>Every man that is ſick, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the ground of his ſickneſs</hi> and <hi>diſtemper;</hi> but the Light which every man is enlightned withall, ſhewes unto him his ſin; for which ſake the Wrath of God cometh and abideth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; that all may ſee your Compariſon is made in the blindneſs of your hearts, which is filled with the groſs Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that you cannot compare Spiritual things with Spiritual;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14.</note> neither indeed can you natural men (who ſay <hi>people are left without excuſe by a natural light</hi>) diſcern the things of God; for they alone are Spiritually diſcerned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts ſay, <hi>VVe diſcover much Ignorance, when we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know what example they have out of the Scriptures, for taking Forty Pounds Sallary,</hi> and <hi>two ſhares of Land a year for preaching.</hi> For they ſay, <hi>Chriſt and his Apoſtles had a compleat Maintenance, and their Salaries is no more.</hi> And again the Prieſts ſay, <hi>They are commanded to take pains, and to beſtow labour to attain ability to diſcharge their Callings, and ſo have another reaſon to require Maintenance, than they that were Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſent, and officiated, and furniſhed by the Spirit of God:</hi> That they ſay, <hi>they do not receive it as Alms,</hi> or <hi>Charity from the peoples free-wil, but as their due debt;</hi> That they ſay, <hi>they may not onely receive it when it is given to them, but alſo may with a good conſcience Sue for it, when it is detained.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97735:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As for Ignorance, that is in abundance ſhewed forth in your ſelves; and it doth betray you, in that it leads you to utter forth your folly, in pleading ſo for your own covetous ends; but do you think that all people are as full of Ignorance and Blindneſs as your ſelves, that they cannot ſee your gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs after the earthly things, which (under a pretence of preaching the Goſpel) you would hurd up to your ſelves? Was there ever ſuch a generation of Covetous Teachers as you are, who (under a pretence of preaching the Goſpel) would gather to your ſelves (if it were in your power) all the ſubſtance people ſhould live upon? And yet ſay, <hi>you receive it not as Almes, or Charity from the people.</hi> Nay you ſay, <hi>you may Sue for it with a good conſcience:</hi> But may not all ſee by this, that you are the men whoſe conſciences the hot Iron hath ſeared? Oh what unſavourineſs and greedineſs appears amongſt you, that have pretended to be Preachers of the Goſpel of peace unto the people, and now tell them, <hi>If they detain your Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Wages, you may go to Law with them for it!</hi> Oh what <hi>Nathaniel VVhite,</hi> Thou that haſt been cryed up for a Paſtor of a Congregation ſo long! Will the people of <hi>Bermuda</hi> bring thee no longer their <hi>free-will-Offerings,</hi> which thou once told them was <hi>their duty to do?</hi> Will they not bring thee <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Rewards,</hi> as they uſe to do? Muſt thou now go to Law for thy Maintenance? Would it not have been thought a ſtrange thing ſome years ago, to have heard ſuch a word from thee, as to ſay thou mightſt with a good conſcience ſue for Wages for preaching? Is not the Proverb fulfilled upon thee? art thou not <hi>turned with the Dog to the Vomit again,</hi> and thy two Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren <hi>Burre</hi> and <hi>Brown?</hi> Where do any of you read, that <hi>Eſay, Jeremy, Ezekiel, Micah,</hi> or <hi>any of the Prophets;</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> or <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>any of the Apoſtles,</hi> told people <hi>that they might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully go to Law with them, if they would not give them ſo many <hi>ſhares of Land,</hi>
               </hi> or <hi>ſo much <hi>Salary</hi> by the year,</hi> or <hi>ſo much <hi>Sugar, Indico,</hi>
               </hi> or <hi>Tobacco,</hi> which many of your Brethren in this <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> preach for, and go to Law with their Hearers for, when they will not pay them it? Yea, and with them alſo, which never heard them; but witneſſes againſt their deceit and covetouſneſs; and witneſſes Chriſt the unchangeable Prieſt,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97735:9"/>who gives them true knowledge, who is the end of the firſt Prieſt-hood, and the Law alſo, by which Tythes was to be paid; and ſo they who witneſs him, ſees you; that are now ſpeaking of going to Law with people for Maintenance, to be a company of greedy Apoſtates, who (like Wolves) would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and go to Law with people, when for conſcience ſake they cannot put into your mouths, nor feed you with gifts and rewards, as thou <hi>Nathaniel White</hi> haſt been, by theſe in <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muda;</hi> whom thou haſt gathered into thy own Form, to follow after thy own Traditions, which thou call'ſt <hi>Church-Order;</hi> and indeed is the <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>New-Englands Church,</hi> after the Order of which, thou waſt made a Paſtor; and though thou haſt not partook with them in ſhedding the Saints blood, yet thy envy hath no leſs appeared than theirs; witneſs <hi>thy praying,</hi> in the hearing of <hi>George Rofe, <hi>That God would open the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates eyes, that they might ſee how they had given leave to have the people ſeduced.</hi>
               </hi> That your taking of pains, which you three Prieſts tell of, is through envy: For you being not immediately called of God, nor furniſhed by his Spirit, as you confeſs you are not; your preaching muſt needs be by your own Inventions; through which you can never beget any to God, though you can make them <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> and <hi>Favorites</hi> unto you, that they will ſtand up with you in envy againſt the Truth; and ſo long as they put into your mouths, and feed you with gifts and rewards, ſo long you will cry <hi>Peace, peace;</hi> but when not, then <hi>you will prepare War:</hi> like your Brethren, whom <hi>Micah</hi> the true Prophet <hi>cryed againſt, Mich.</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>The Prophets, Chriſt, and his Apoſtles had a ſufficient Maintenance,</hi> and <hi>your Salaries</hi> are no more; I charge you all, to ſhew where one of the <hi>true Prophets, Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>his Apoſtles,</hi> had <hi>Forty Pounds Salary,</hi> and <hi>Two ſhares of Land a year,</hi> and <hi>ſo much weight of Tabacco</hi> as you have; that it is but a perverting the Truth, to take their words to plead for your own covetous ends: And do you not think that they who fear the Lord on that Iſland, takes notice of your co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, and of thy unſtableneſs <hi>Nathaniel White;</hi> who once pretended a great zeal for holineſs, and is now turned to ſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and playing with them, who (when thou hadſt a ſincerity in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97735:10"/>thee) was thy enemies; but now, thou being turned from it, they can joyn with thee, and thou with them, in ſporting, and gaming; but doſt thou think that they who fear the Lord, are not burthened to ſee ſuch things? And doſt thou not think that they ſee ſuch things not to be of God, but of the wicked one? Who ever rejected the Truth and its Reproofs, as you three Prieſts have done; but the Truth is over you, which will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe your torment.</p>
            <p>And whereas you deſire all men <hi>to take notice of the malice of your Adverſaries, for queſtioning you about your Salaries:</hi> For you ſay, <hi>they are paid, not by them whom you preach unto; but ariſeth</hi> (you ſay) <hi>from the devotion of the firſt Founders and Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of that Colony; ſo that by your Preaching, the Inhabitants are not put to one peny more charges by us,</hi> ſay you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But nevertheleſs, though you have not your Wages from them whom you Preach unto, this doth not make it that you are no Hirelings; for we believe you make little mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>whom you have it on, ſo you have it.</hi> And who is there that knoweth the ſtate of that Iſland, and doth not know how much the people thereof are oppreſſed by them, whom you ſay payes you your Salaries; that it is ſtill but the money of Oppreſſion. For doth not the Inhabitants of the Iſland, whom you preach unto, pay unto them (of whom you receive your Wages) <hi>one peny half peny</hi> forth <hi>of every pound of Tobacco</hi> that they ſend for <hi>England,</hi> except they get it away by ſtealth; which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted great Oppreſſion; much more then that of Tythes? And do not they <hi>(your Maſters)</hi> who Hire you, tell the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Iſland, that they take <hi>that penny half penny out of every Pound of Tobacco in part for paying you your Wages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo for your challenging of us, whom you account your Adverſaries, <hi>to prove that the Inhabitants are put to one penny charge by you for your Preaching:</hi> We ſay, You need not have made ſuch a great challenge; for we can eaſily prove, and bring the Inhabitants to witneſs for us, that you put them every year to many a penny charge, by Repairing the Houſes you dwell in; and if they do it not juſt when you would have them, will you not frown at them? So this your cover, is rip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97735:10"/>open, and your challenge returned upon your ſelves, that your nakedneſs more and more appears; for the day hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken forth, which makes all your deceit manifeſt; and Praiſes be unto the Lord, many he hath viſited by it; who begin to ſee your folly and weakneſs concerning the things of God, and are declining from you, that they may be brought to know the Lord their Teacher, by his Law which he hath written in their hearts; and this is the Lord fulfilling for his own mercy ſake, in ſpite of all envious men, who gnawes their Tongues for grief and pain.</p>
            <p>Again the Prieſts ſay in their Anſwer to our 17th Querie, which was concerning their Preaching by an Hour-glaſs: <hi>That they have the Warrant of the cuſtom of the Churches of God for it;</hi> which they ſay <hi>is a ſufficient Warrant againſt all contentious ſpirits; and they bring</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. <hi>to prove it by.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That place of Scripture doth not ſpeak any thing of the Apoſtles preaching <hi>by an Hour-glaſs,</hi> as you do; that we can juſtly contend for the Truth againſt your Deceit in this. And I charge you three Prieſts to prove where ever there was ſuch a Cuſtom among the true gathered Churches, who was gathered by the Spirit of the Lord, and witneſſed Praying, and Propheſying by it. Are you not aſhamed to ſcandalize the Churches of. God, in ſaying it was their cuſtom <hi>to preach by an Hour-glaſs?</hi> But will any that have read the Scripture believe you? Certainly none, but who are willingly as blind as your ſelves.</p>
            <p>Again, The Prieſts to prove the <hi>ſprinkling</hi> of <hi>Infants <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi>
               </hi> they bring <hi>the Command</hi> of God to <hi>Abraham to Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe:</hi> And they ſay, <hi>ſprinkling of Infants</hi> (which they call Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm) <hi>came in in the room of it.</hi> For they ſay, <hi>Though they be different in the External Sign,</hi> yet <hi>they are one and the ſame in the Inward and Spiritual Grace, ſignified by the Signs;</hi> for they ſay, <hi>both Baptiſm</hi> and <hi>Circumciſion, ſignifie a being in Covenant with God; and Gods Command to</hi> Abraham <hi>to Circumciſe, will warrant Baptiſing of Infants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As for <hi>ſprinkling of Infants,</hi> that (without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie) was never commanded of God; but is an Invention of the Popes, who commanded it to be done with <hi>the ſign of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97735:11"/>the Croſs;</hi> and though you have left it off, and are become diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient <hi>to your father <hi>the Pope;</hi>
               </hi> yet nevertheleſs he was the firſt Author of it: Though you diſobey his Command, and will not do it with his ſign, the Croſs, but do it after your own Invention, and ſo you are found acting contrary to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Rule, by adding your own Inventions. For they never received a Command, neither gave a Command to <hi>ſprinkle Infants,</hi> and ſo you are found out of their Rule, and <hi>your fathers Rule</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> alſo, and are not faithful to his Church, which is your Churches Mother, that you as Rebellious Children kick againſt him; yet you may thank him for firſt Inſtituting this Ordinance (as you call it) of ſprinkling Infants, which you in your ignorance ſay, <hi>The Command of God to</hi> Abraham <hi>to Circumciſe, will warrant you in.</hi> But all whoſe eyes God hath opened, out of that great ſlumber you are in, ſees that the Command given to <hi>Abraham</hi> to Circumciſe, will no more warrant you in ſprinkling of Infants your way, than it will do the Pope in his way. For we know Circumciſion was given a Seal unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> of the righteouſneſs of Faith, which he had being uncircumciſed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. but as for your ſprinkling of Infants, we know nothing that it is a Seal of; except of your own ignorance. And as for your ſaying, that ſprinkling of Infants came in the room of Circumciſion, do you not think that all, whoſe underſtanding the Lord hath opened by his eternal Spirit, will take notice of your ignorance and blindneſs in this thing? For Circumciſion, as you may read, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28, 29. is not that of the Outward in the Fleſh, but is of the Heart, in the Spirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That all who are not blind, may ſee that Circumciſion of the Heart with the Spirit, endeth that of the Outward in the Fleſh,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.15. That as for your ſprinkling of Infants, it is but a meer Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and was never commanded of God, as Circumciſion in its time was; neither ever was it practiſed among any we read of, that in the Apoſtles daies, by the Spirit, was gathered into fellowſhip with the Lord; for they ſpoke of <hi>one Faith, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> and were <hi>Baptiſed by one Spirit into one Body,</hi> and ſo was <hi>in oneneſs <hi>of mind</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>judgement, one</hi> with <hi>another;</hi> for the Spirit by which they were Baptiſed into the death and ſuffering
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97735:11"/>of Chriſt, made them <hi>of one mind</hi> and <hi>ſoul;</hi> which you <hi>three Prieſts,</hi> who plead for the Popiſh inſtitution, ſprinkling of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are not. For do you not differ among your ſelves about it? One crying of it up to be done <hi>after his way,</hi> and to whoſe Children <hi>he will;</hi> and another, <hi>another way,</hi> to <hi>whom he will;</hi> and ſo are in your ignorance at difference amongſt your ſelves? But do you not think people begins to take notice of you, and to ſee your folly; though you joyn all your Forces together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Truth, and though you joyn in union with Death and Hell, and make lies your Refuge? <hi>Yet Judgement is laid to the Line, &amp; Righteouſneſs to the Plummet; and Hail ſhal ſweep away the refuge of lies, and your agreement with Hell ſhall be broken, and your Covenant with Death diſannulled,</hi> that the Truth may appear unto all, who have a deſire to walk therein, from under that <hi>(ſad, &amp; ſable Cloud of Obloquie)</hi> which thou <hi>Nathaniel White</hi> uſed to tell of; which indeed lies thick upon thee, that thou canſt not ſee that thou art fallen into the ſnare; but joyns with the other two Prieſts, <hi>Brown,</hi> and <hi>Burre</hi> in thoſe things, which ſometime thou wouldſt have been aſhamed to have owned and pleaded for; <hi>But evil men and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers wax worſe and worſe, deceiving, and being deceived.</hi> That this is written for the ſake of ſuch (in that Iſland of <hi>Bermuda</hi>) as might be deceived by you, by your perverting and ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing the Truth in your envy and hatred againſt it;<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.13.</note> which no little hath appeared, ſince firſt the Truth was bore teſtimony unto before you and your Hearers; a Remnant of which, the Lord will yet gather from the mouths of all ſuch dumb Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, that he might teach them himſelf according to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and put his Law in their mindes, and his fear in their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.16.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts in their Anſwer to our laſt <hi>Querie,</hi> which was concerning ſinging <hi>Davids</hi> conditions in Rime and Meeter: To this they ſay, <hi>That God is no reſpecter of Perſons, but giveth the ſame condition to all his ſervants:</hi> And they ſay, <hi>They have an expreſs Command for ſinging of Pſalmes,</hi> Col. 3.16. Jam. 5.13. And <hi>the example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles,</hi> Matth. 26.30. Acts 16.25. And they ſay, <hi>If we think that we can find more fit Pſalms than Chriſt acknowledged to be holy Scripture, we may ſpeak our mindes;</hi> and they ſay, <hi>they will anſwer it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97735:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> None of theſe Scriptures, which you have mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſpeak any thing of ſinging <hi>Davids Prayers, Quakings,</hi> and <hi>Lamentations,</hi> in <hi>Rime</hi> and <hi>Meeter,</hi> as you do: for <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms were turned into meeter by the Proteſtants ſince they turned from the Papiſts: Neither do we believe that your Hearers, whom you ſing with, are in <hi>Davids</hi> conditions; but are as far from them as you Covetous Teachers are your ſelves: that we know, and believe, that you cannot admoniſh one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in <hi>Pſalms, Hymns</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual Songs;</hi> nor ſing with grace in your hearts unto the Lord: which that place of Scripture, which you mention, ſaith, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. For you are ſuch whoſe hearts are exerciſed with Covetous Practices; who have forſaken the right way, and are following the way of <hi>Balaam</hi> the ſon of <hi>Boſor,</hi> who loved the wages of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, as you do, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14, 15. That you are far from <hi>Davids</hi> Condition, and from ſinging unto the Lord <hi>with grace in your hearts:</hi> for they are carried away with Covetouſneſs, as your fruits make it manifeſt; in your ſo much pleading and preaching for filthy lucre; which Chriſt and his Apoſtles (whoſe words you Covetous men are not aſhamed to ſpeak of) declared againſt. And you need not tell us of Chriſts owning <hi>Davids</hi> Writings to be holy Scripture: for we know, that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was a man that feared God, and hated ſuch covetous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, as you are found guilty of: But we know no command <hi>Tho. Sternhold</hi> nor <hi>John Hopkins</hi> had (nor yet the <hi>New-England</hi> blood-thirſty-men) for putting his Writings in Rime and Meeter; neither to adde their own Inventions to them, to make them, that Drunkards, and Swearers might ſing them in a Tune: which even thou, <hi>Nathaniel VVhite,</hi> doſt often bid them keep, when they are not diligent in ſinging as thou wouldſt have them, but miſſes Tune. And that place you mention, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.30. ſpeaks nothing of Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, ſinging <hi>Davids</hi> Writings, but ſaith, <hi>they ſung an Hymn:</hi> And we know, <hi>Paul ſung Praiſes unto the Lord;</hi> as in <hi>Acts</hi> 16.25. though he was put into the Stocks, and received many Stripes, for reproving the Spirit of Divination in the Woman, who through South-ſaying, brought in her Maſter great gain: but when he ſaw the hope of it was gone, he went
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97735:12"/>about to perſecute the Servants of the Lord, in whom the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth was; and haled them before the Magiſtrates, as <hi>Nathaniel White, George Rofe</hi> was, for ſpeaking to thee; that when thou perceivedſt that thy deceit was like to be laid open to the people, cryed out to the Magiſtrates, beſeeching them <hi>not to let him speak there.</hi> But <hi>Nathaniel VVhite,</hi> if thou hadſt ſpoken nothing but ſound words, which could not have been condemned, why didſt thou not ſtand by them? For if thy Church be the true Church, it is built upon that which the gates of Hell cannot prevail againſt. But you Prieſts, being erred through Covetouſneſs; and your Church being of her off-ſpring, which is to be burned with fire; and you having loſt the Spiritual Weapons, you are fain to fly <hi>to the Mountains and Hills</hi> for defence; but they cannot defend you, nor cover you; but your deceit and nakedneſs daily appeareth, as it doth in this thing; your pleading <hi>for the ſinging of Davids Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> in <hi>rime</hi> and <hi>meeter;</hi> which conditions you your ſelves never knew: that though you ſay God giveth the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to all his Servants, yet you are not come to the Servants ſtate, but are (with many of your hearers) like a company of untamed Heifers, who are not accuſtomed to the yoke; nor are not yet come to know the fear of the Lord, which is the beginning of wiſdom; nor to depart from iniquity, which is the good underſtanding; that you are not like to ſing with the Spirit, and with underſtanding, ſo long as you live in thoſe things which the Spirit teſtifies againſt: That if you three Prieſts truly ſearch your ſelves, and let the Witneſs of God riſe in you, it will let you ſee, that you are ſuch as <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of in that place you mention, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.12. who were fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into the condemnation, and ſo are ſhort of the condition <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of in ver. 13. in which <hi>every one that was afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed might pray;</hi> and <hi>he that was merry ſing Pſalms.</hi> For you may alſo read <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.22. <hi>That he whoſe tongue is not bridled, his Religion is vain:</hi> And how had <hi>Jonathan Burre</hi> his tongue bridled, when he called <hi>George Rofe Butter-whore,</hi> and <hi>prating Aſſe?</hi> But it may be <hi>Nathaniel White,</hi> thou wilt ſay, thou doſt not own him in it: but tell me then how it comes to paſſe, that thou joyneſt with <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>Brown,</hi> in pleading for ſuch
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97735:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>things, as here before-mentioned, which was ſet down in you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> own Paper by way of Anſwer to our <hi>Queryes:</hi> which Paper was given into my hands, with all your Names to it.</p>
            <p>And many things more I might have gathered out of it, than here is; by which I might have manifeſted your erring from the Scriptures of Truth: but ſo much here is diſcovered of your Blindneſs, and Ignorance of the things of God, that any who love the appearance of the Witneſs of Truth in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, may eaſily ſee of what ſort of Teachers you are.</p>
            <p>And you the Inhabitants of <hi>Bermuda,</hi> who are following on after thoſe Traditions, which theſe men (which before I have ſpoken of) lead you unto, that you may confider what you joyn with, and receive for Doctrine; for, as you may read in the Scripture, there were ſome that taught the Commandments of men for Doctrine, and ſo through their own Traditions made void the Law of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.9. <hi>Mark</hi> 7.11. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14 20, 21.</note> and the Righteouſneſs which is of Faith, which who cometh to know, knows it to end all thoſe things which ſtood in the Law, contained in Ordinances, and divers Waſhings, and ſuch things which was impoſed, until the time of Reformation, that the Seed ſhould come; which ends all the Types, Figures, and Shadows, and gives to ſee beyond all external things, which the minds of people are after, until they come to feel that Righteouſneſs which is of Faith, revealed in them, which ſaith on this wiſe, <hi>Say not in thy heart, Who ſhall aſcend into Heaven? that is, to bring Chriſt down from above: Or, who ſhall deſcend into the deep? that is, to bring up Chriſt again from the dead: But what ſaith it? the Word is nigh thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou mayeſt do it: and this is the Word of Faith which we preach,</hi> Deut. 30.14. Rom. 10.6, 7, 8.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Wind-mill,</hi> in <hi>Martins Le Grand,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
